chapter 28
for several days after leaving Nantuck pocket. Nothing above hatches was seen
of Captain Ahab. The mates regularly relieved each other at the watches, and
for all that could be seen to the contrary, they seemed to be the only
commanders of the ship, only they sometimes issued from the cabin with
orders so sudden and perempter that, after all, it was plain they but commanded vicariously.
Yes, their supreme lord and dictator was there, though hitherto unseen by any
eyes. was not permitted to penetrate into the now sacred retreat of the cabin.
Every time I ascended to the deck from my watches below, I instantly gazed a to
mark if any strange face were visible, for my first vague disquitude touching
the unknown captain, now in the seclusion of the sea, became almost a
perturbation. This was strangely heightened at times by the ragged
Elijah's diabolical incoherences uninvitedly recurring to me with a
subtle energy I could not have before conceived of. But poorly could I
withstand them, much as in other moods I was almost ready to smile at the solemn
whimsicalities of that outlandish prophet of the warves. But whatever it
was, of apprehensiveness or uneasiness, to call it so, which I felt, whenever I
came to look about me in the ship, it seemed against all warranty to cherish
such emotions. For though the harpooners, with the great body of the
crew, were a far more barbaric, heathenish, and mottly set, than any of
the tame merchant ship companies which my previous experiences had made me
acquainted with. Still, I ascribed this, and rightly ascribed it, to the fierce
uniqueness of the very nature of that wild Scandinavian vocation, in which I
had so abandonedly embarked, but it was especially the aspect of the three chief
officers of the ship, the mates, which was most forcibly calculated to allay
these colorless misgivings, and induce confidence and cheerfulness in every
presentment of the voyage. Three better, more likely sea officers and men, each
in his own different way, could not readily be found, and they were, every
one of them Americans, a Nantucketer, a vineyard, a capeman. Now it being
Christmas when the ship shot from outer harbor for a space we had biting polar
weather, though all the time running away from it to the southward, and by
every degree in minute of latitude which we sailed, gradually leaving that
merciless winter and all its intolerable weather behind us. It was one of those
less lowering, but still gray and gloomy enough mornings of the transition, when,
with a fair wind, the ship was rushing through the water with a vindictive sort
of leaping and melancholy rapidity, that as I mounted to the deck at the call of
the for noon watch, so soon as I leveled my glance toward the taffil, foroding
shivers ran over me. Reality outran apprehension. Captain Ahab stood upon his quarter deck.
There seemed no sign of common bodily illness about him, nor of the recovery
for many. He looked like a man cut away from the stake, when the fire has
overrunningly wasted all the limbs without consuming them, or taking away
one particle from their compacted, aged robustness. His whole high broad form
seemed made of solid bronze and shaped in an unalterable mold like Chelini's
cast Perseus. Threading its way out from among his gray hairs, and continuing
right down one side of his tawny, scorched face and neck, till it
disappeared in his clothing, you saw a slender, rodlike mark, lividly whitish.
It resembled that perpendicular seam sometimes made in the straight lofty
trunk of a great tree, when the upper lightning tearingly darts down it, and
without wrenching a single twig, peels and grooves out the bark from top to
bottom, air running off into the soil, leaving the tree still greenly alive,
but branded. Whether that mark was born with him, or whether it was the scar
left by some desperate wound, no one could certainly say, by some tacit
consent throughout the voyage, little or no allusion was made to it, especially
by the mates. But once Tash Teego's senior, an old gay head Indian among the
crew, superstitiously asserted that not till he was full 40 years old did Ahab
become that way branded, and then it came upon him not in the fury of any
mortal Frey, but in an elemental strife at sea. Yet this wild hint seemed
inferentially negatived by what a gray mansman insinuated. An old sephilcrrol
man who having never before sailed out of Nantucket had never heir this laid
eye upon wild Ahab. Nevertheless, the old sea traditions, the immemorial
creduities, popularly invested this old mansmen with prednatural powers of
discernment, so that no white sailor seriously contradicted him when he said
that if ever Captain Ahab should be tranquily laid out, which might hardly
come to pass, so he muttered, "Then whoever should do that last office for
the dead would find a birthark on him from crown to soul."
So powerfully did the whole grim aspect of Ahab affect me, and the livid brand
which streaked it, that for the first few moments I hardly noted that not a
little of this overbearing grimness, was owing to the barbaric white leg upon
which he partly stood. It had previously come to me that this ivory leg had at
sea been fashioned from the polished bone of a sperm whale's jaw.
I he was dismasted off Japan, said the old gayhead Indian once, but like his
dismasted craft, he shipped another mast without coming home for it. He has a
quiver of them. I was struck with the singular posture he maintained. Upon
each side of the Peekquad's quarter deck, and pretty close to the mizen
shrouds, there was an augur hole bored about half an inch or so into the plank.
His bone legs steadied in that hole, one arm elevated and holding by a shroud,
Captain Ahab stood erect, looking straight out beyond the ship's ever
pitching prow. There was an infinity of firmst fortitude, a determinate,
unsurderable willfulness in the fixed and fearless forward dedication of that
glance. Not a word he spoke, nor did his officers say ought to him, though by all
their minutestous gestures and expressions they plainly showed the
uneasy, if not painful, consciousness of being under a troubled master eye. And
not only that, but moody, stricken Ahab stood before them with a crucifixion in
his face, in all the nameless, regal, overbearing dignity of some mighty woe.
air long from his first visit in the air, he withdrew into his cabin, but
after that morning he was everyday visible to the crew, either standing in
his pivot hole, or seated upon an ivory stool he had, or heavily walking the
deck. As the sky grew less gloomy, indeed began to grow a little genial, he
became still less and less a recluse, as if, when the ship had sailed from home,
nothing but the dead wintry bleakness of the sea had then kept him so secluded.
And by and by it came to pass that he was almost continually in the air, but
as yet for all that he said or perceptibly did on the at last sunny
deck, he seemed as unnecessary there as another mast. But the Peekquad was only
making a passage now, not regularly cruising. Nearly all wailing
preparatives needing supervision, the mates were fully competent to, so that
there was little or nothing out of himself to employ or excite Ahab now.
and thus chase away for that one interval the clouds that layer upon
layer were piled upon his brow. As ever all clouds choose the loftiest peaks to
pile themselves upon.
Nevertheless, the warm warbling persuasiveness of the pleasant holiday
weather we came to seemed gradually to charm him from his mood. For as when the
red cheicked dancing girls, April and May, trip home to the wintry,
misanthropic woods, even the barest, ruggedest, most thunderloven old oak
will at least send forth some few green sprouts to welcome such gladhearted
visitants. So Ahab did in the end a little respond to the playful allurings
of that girish air. More than once did he put forth the faint blossom of a look
which in any other man would have soon flowered out in a smile.